Russel V. Lee family papers M2109
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Russel V. Lee family papers
ca. 1895-2014
1940s-1970s
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lee, Russel V.
Lee, Philip R. (Philip Randolph)
Lee, Dorothy Rusk
Chadwick, Margaret Lee
M2109
1.75 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Russel Van Arsdale Lee founded the Palo Alto Medical Clinic (PAMC), one of the first group practice clinics in the United States. He was a champion of rights for abortion, prepaid medical care and free drugs for addicts, and a leader in health education. His five sons all became doctors. Philip R. Lee's focus in research and teaching was in health policy and he authored numerous articles and co-authored or edited numerous books.
Content Description
The collection contains orrespondence, photographs, printed material, scrapbooks, newspaper articles, and ephemera relating to the Lee family, the Palo Alto Medical Clinic and Stanford Hospital, and the careers of Russel V. Lee and Philip R. Lee.
Related Materials
Philip R. Lee papers; Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives, Stanford University Libraries.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Note that the scrapbook in box 4 and the photo album in box 5 are fragile and should be handled with particular care.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Philip R. Lee, 2016. Accession MSS 2016-011.
Physicians.; Medicine.; Clinics -- California -- Palo Alto; Lee, Russel V.; Lee, Philip R. (Philip Randolph); Lee, Philip R. (Philip Randolph); Lee, Dorothy Rusk; Chadwick, Margaret Lee
- Leo Eloesser (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Russel V. Lee and Dorothy Lee: thank you from Mayor Shephard re Foothills Park; song for Russ and Do's 5oth anniversay (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Philip R. Lee - correspondence, 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Rev. Theodore Lee, Anna Wray [Lee] and family - clippings and telegrams (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Russel V. Lee: "Vacation on Vancouver" - published (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Russel V. Lee family tree (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Russel V. Lee - draft of autobiography (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Russel V. Lee - papers; draft letter from Kitty Lee (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Russel V. Lee - speeches, papers, statements, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter to Douglas S. Winslow, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Poem by Jeff Hook dedicated to Russel V. Lee, April 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Russel V. Lee - clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Russel V. Lee - Herbert Hoover Medal, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "A dipperful of humanity," Margaret Lee Chadwick, with happy birthday annotation to brother, April 27, 1978 (Box 1)
- Russel V. Lee - "To my kids," July 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Dorothy Lee - acknowledgements of condolences re death of Dorothy Lee (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Russel V. Lee - Memoirs, 1983, Part I - II, spiral bound. "Here stands a man: the memoirs of Russel Van Arsdale Lee, 1983, bound. (Box 2)
- Yearbook: Madrono 1941, published by the students of Palo Alto High School (Box 2)
- Stanford University School of Medicine Forty Careers in Medicine (Box 2)
- Historic Houses III: San Juan Neighborhood, Stanford University (Box 3)
- Books published by Russel V. Lee: No Gravy on the Vest; The Menace of Madness in High Places (Box 3)
- Belonging: Wiseman, Woolverton, Griswold, Angel, compiled by Helen Angel Fullenwider, March 1991 (Box 3)
- Photographs - trip through Utah by Paul, Russel and Margaret Lee, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Lee family photographs - Spanish Fork, Utah (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Lee photographs (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographs - trip to India (Philip Lee and Ed O'Rom?) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Palo Alto Community Book, Guy C. Miller, 1952 (Box 3)
- Russel V. Lee and Dorothy Lee Womack: golden anniversary invitation, handwritten congratulations from Lyndon B. Johnson (Flat-box 4, Folder 1)
- Lee family album: clippings from inside the album about unnecessary medical procedures and Dr. Philip Lee's comments (Flat-box 4, Folder 2)
- Lee family album, annotated - Spanish Fork (Utah), Margaret, Joe, miscellaneous (Flat-box 4)
- Scrapbook Dr. Philip M. Lee - clippings, some photographs, 1962; Certificate of Appreciation San Jose Lions Club, 1962-1963; 3 letters, 1962 (fragile) (Flat-box 4)
- Palo Alto-Stanford Hospital newspaper articles, September 1959-June 1960 (Flat-box 5, Map-folder 1)
- Dr. Russel Lee and Dr. Philip Lee - newspaper cover stories, April 1964-Deceber 1993 (Flat-box 5, Map-folder 2)
- Stanford feature section of Peninsula Living, April 30, 1960 (Flat-box 5, Map-folder 2)
- Lee/Estes remodel, 620 Los Trancos Rd., Palo Alto, CA blueprints (Flat-box 5, Map-folder 3)
- The election, Washington Post, November 6, 1980: Ronald Reagan wins over President Carter (Flat-box 5, Map-folder 4)
- Family photograph album, some with captions. Very fragile. (Flat-box 6)